<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                      -->
<!--                                                    -->
<!--         Git for Authors                            -->
<!--                                                    -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2016  Robert A. Beezer, David Farmer -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.       -->

<!-- <frontmatter xml:id="index"> -->
<frontmatter>

    <titlepage>
        <author>
            <personname>Robert A. Beezer</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematics and Computer Science</department>
            <institution>University of Puget Sound</institution>
            <email>beezer@pugetsound.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>David Farmer</personname>
            <institution>American Institute of Mathematics</institution>
            <email>farmer@aimath.org</email>
        </author>

        <date>DRAFT <today /> DRAFT</date>
    </titlepage>

    <colophon>
        <copyright>
            <year>2016</year>
            <holder>Robert A. Beezer, David Farmer</holder>
            <shortlicense>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled <q>GNU Free Documentation License</q>.</shortlicense>
        </copyright>
    </colophon>

    <preface>
        <title>How to Read This Book</title>

        <p>The essential concepts of <c>git</c> are treated in the first four chapters, they should be read thoroughly and carefully, in order.  <xref ref="solo" />, <xref ref="friends" />, and <xref ref="control" />, treat the cases, respectively, of one, several, and many collaborators, with very different organizational models, but the concepts are universal to all three models.</p>

        <p>Eventually you will find more intricate topics in <xref ref="merge-conflict" /> and <xref ref="branch-management" /> necessary or useful, and maybe both.  <xref ref="oops" /> explains ways to backup and correct mistakes.  <xref ref="miscellany" /> is a grabbag of short topics that do not fit naturally in the early material and would have just been a distraction.  At some point familiarize yourself with what is on-offer there.  The appendices contain technical information that might change over time, in addition to reference material.</p>
    </preface>

</frontmatter>
