<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                      -->
<!--                                                    -->
<!--         Git for Authors                            -->
<!--                                                    -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2016  Robert A. Beezer, David Farmer -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.       -->

<appendix xml:id="quick-reference">
    <title>Quick Reference</title>

    <p>Cheat sheets for common tasks</p>


    <list xml:id="eight-step">
        <title>The Eight-Step: Adding Commits to the Definitive Repository</title>

        <introduction>
            <p>We will describe the process of moving commits on a <q>topic</q> branch in a local repository to the master branch of a definitive repository where you have permission to push, and the repository is configured as a remote in your local repository.  Eventually, the logic of this procedure will become second nature.</p>
        </introduction>

        <ol>
            <li>
                <p><c>git checkout master</c></p>
                <p>Prepare to bring the local master branch up-to-date.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
                <p><c>git pull</c></p>
                <p>Pull new commits from the definitive repository into the local master branch.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
                <p><c>git checkout topic</c></p>
                <p>Move back to the topic branch (which will have a different name).</p>
            </li>

            <li>
                <p><c>git rebase master</c></p>
                <p>Move the branch point of the topic branch to the tip of updated master.  Resolve any conflicts which occur during the replay phase of the rebase.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
                <p><c>git checkout master</c></p>
                <p>Move back to the local master branch in preparation for modifying it.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
                <p><c>git branch -d topic</c></p>
                <p>The topic branch pointer is obsolete as it duplicates the master branch pointer.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
                <p><c>git merge topic</c></p>
                <p>Use a fast-forward merge to bring the topic branch into the master branch.</p>
            </li>

            <li>
                <p><c>git push</c></p>
                <p>Move new commits on the local master branch to the master branch of the definitive repository.</p>
            </li>
        </ol>
    </list>




</appendix>
